Guide to the John J. Cushing Correspondence
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
John J. Cushing Correspondence
1853-1873
1853-1857
Ms Coll 35
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
0.25
(1 box, 33 items)
John J. Cushing was an early homeopathic physician in San Francisco. The collection consists of letters to his family.
Cushing, John J., 1822-1879
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased, 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
John J. Cushing was born in Providence, Rhode Island on February 14, 1822, the son Daniel Cooke Cushing (1783-1830), a merchant in Providence, and Susan Barrett Cushing (1786-1862). With a medical diploma from an unidentified medical school, he moved to San Francisco in 1853 and began practice as one of the earliest homeopathic physicians in San Francisco. He served as first president of the Pacific Homoeopathic Medical Society in 1874. In 1856 he married Harriet Reed Barlow of Burlington, Vermont, who was a school teacher in San Francisco. In 1873 he moved to Marin County about six miles from Sausalito where he homesteaded property and built a sanitorium which he named Blithedale. He died at Blithedale on September 3, 1879.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of letters written by John J. Cushing from San Francisco to his mother, brother Edward, and sister Susan Cushing Cheney, in Providence, Rhode Island. They contain information on a wide variety of subjects including his homeopathic medical practice, relations with regular physicians, gold and copper mining (he owned a copper mine in Arizona), economic conditions, social life, San Francisco politics, his marriage, and the construction of his house.
Arrangement
Arranged by date.
Copper mines and mining -- Arizona; Gold mines and mining -- California; Homeopathy -- California; Politics and culture -- California -- San Francisco; California -- Economic conditions; Letters (correspondence); Homeopathic physicians -- California -- San Francisco; Cushing, John J., 1822-1879; Cushing, Edward Jarvis, 1824-1905; Cushing, Susan Barrett, 1786-1862; Cheney, Susan Jarvis Cushing, 1827-; San Francisco Medical Society
- Letters to family, 1853 May-July (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  4 items. Pencil notes written by the manuscript dealer.
- Letters to family, 1853 August-November (Box 1, Folder 2)
  4 items.
- Letters to family, 1854 February-April (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters to family, 1854 September-November (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letters to family, 1855 January-May (Box 1, Folder 5)
  3 items.
- Letters to family, 1856 January-May (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letters to family, 1856 June-December (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Leters to family, 1857 January-February (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letters to family, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  1 letter to Edward urging him to come to California.
- Letters to family, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  3 undated items, one to "Dear Folks" and one each to Edward and his mother.